Nora England Papers
Nettie Lee Benson Latin American Collection
- Series I: Work by Others
  - Koizumi, Junji, "Fate to Suffer: On Mam Notions of Self", presented at American Anthropological Association meeting, 1981 December 5 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Kwachka, Patricia, "Who's Talking to Who/m? The Last Frontier of Discourse,", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "The Syntactic Status of Ergativity in Quiche,", undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "On 'Possession in Aguacatec", presented at the American Anthropological Association, 1974 November (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "A Preliminary Look at Aguacatec Narrative Discourse,", 1979 March (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "Deictic and Non-Deictic Directionals in Aguacatec,", Spring 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "Deictic and Non-Deictic Directionals in Aguacatec", handout for American Anthropological Association presentation, 1981 December (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "Aguacatec Syrtax from a Furctioral Perspective,", 1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "The Cognitive Bases of Case Marking and Ergativity,", 1982 February (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Larsen, Thomas W.,, "Aguacatec 'Set B' Person/Number Markers in the Context of Mamean Language,", undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., "Cognate Grammatical Systems in Historical Linguistics: A Mayan Example,", Fall 1978 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Larsen, Thomas W., and Norman, William M., "Correlates of Ergativity in Mayan Grammar,", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Larsen, Thomas W. and Norman, William M., "Ergativity in Mayan Grammar,", undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Levin, Beth C., "On the Nature of Ergativity", dissertation, 1983 May (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Lingua Descriptive Studies questionnaire, 1977 June (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Lounsbury, Floyd G., "Maya Numeration, Computation, and Calendrical Astronomy,", undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Lowy, Bernard, "Amanita Muscaria and the Thunderbolt Legend in Guatemala and Mexico,", 1974 January-February (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Luckenbach, Alvin H. and Richard S. Levy, "The Implications of Nahua (Aztecan) Lexical Diversity for Mesoamerican Culture-History,", 1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Lutz, Christopher H. and W. George Lovell, "Core and Periphery in Colonial Guatemala", prepared for oral presentation at the symposium on Indian Communities and the State in Guatemala, 1988 March 17 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Lutz, Christopher H. and W. George Lovell, "Survivors on the Move: Maya Migration in Time and Space,", 1991 April 5 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Maldonado Andrés, Juan and Juan Ordoñǝez Domingo, "Practicas y Experiencias Obtenidas en Programas de Alfabetizacion Efectuados en una Comunidad Indigena del Area Mam,", 1974 November (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Mam de Ixtlahua en el Siglo XVIII, 1949 March; 1949 June (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Manelis Klein, Harriet E., "Noun Classifiers in Toba,", circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Manelis Klein, Harriet E., "Location and Direction in TobaL Verbal Morphology,", 1981 July (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Manelis Klein, Harriet E., "The Future Precedes the Past: Time in Toba,", 1987 December (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Martín, Laura, "Mayan Influence in Guatemalan Spanish: A Research Outline and Test Case", presented at American Anthropological Association, 1976 November (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Martín, Laura, "The Emergence of Phonemic Tone in Mocho (Mayan),", 1984 November (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Martín, L., "Convergence and Divergence in Bilingual Narrative: The Bear Story in Spanish and Mocho (Mayan),", 1985 December (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Martín, L., "Language Form and Language Function in Zoot Suit and The Border: A Contribution to the Analysis of the Role of Foreign Language in Film,", 1983 April (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Martín, L., "A Morphological Description of the Aymara Language,", 1969 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Martín, L., "A Phonology of Aymara,", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Martín, L., "Direction/Location and Kanjobal Positional Roots,", 1977 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Martín, L., "Eskimo Words for Snow: A Case Study in the Genesis and Decay of an Anthropological Example,", 1982 December (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Martín, L., "Gringa in the Field: An Anthropological Linguist Struggles to Record a Dying Indian Language,", undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Martin, Jack B., Carol Cypress and Virginia Tommie, "A Dictionary of Miccosukee (Elaponke),", 2006 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Mathiot, Madeleine and Joyce Penfield, "How to Cope with the Mainstream Culture: A Cultural Approach to Bilingual Education,", undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Maxwell, Judith, (PLFM), "Chuj Intransitives: Or When Can an Intransitive Verb Take an Object?,", undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Mayan Linguistics Handouts, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Mayers, Marvin K., "Doublets and Triplets in Pocomchi (Maya: Guatemala) Discourse,", undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - McCreery, David, "State Power, Indigenous Communities, and Land in Nineteenth Century Guatemala, 1820-1920", master copy of draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - McGee, R. John., "Metaphorical Substitution in a Lacandon Maya Ritual Song,", undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - McQuown, Norman A., "El papel de la lengua materna en la educación nacional,", 1970 April (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Miracle, Andrew W., Jr., "Bicultural Education: Congruency and Conflict Between Formal Schooling and Informal Education--The Case of the Aymara of Bolivia,", 1975 December 3 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Miracle, Andrew W., Jr., "Alphabets and National Policy: The Case of Guarani,", undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Mithun, Marianne, "Is Basic Word Order Universal,", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Mixteco de Santa María Peñoles, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Moore, G. Alexander, Jr., "The Validation of Ascribed Status: Gentry Careers in Guatemala,", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Moore, G. Alexander, "Walt Disney World: Bounded Ritual Space and the Playful Pilgramage Center,", 1980 October (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Moore, Denny, "Identity and Literacy in Brazilian Indian Languages,", undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Myhill, John, "A Comparative Study of Topic and Focus Constructions with Special Reference to Tzotzil,", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Niño-Murcia, Mercedes, "Linguistic Purism in Cuzco, Peru: A Historical Perspective,", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Niño-Murcia, Mercedes, Various articles, 1996 May (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Niño-Murcia, Mercedes, "Spaces of Identity: A Case for Indigenous Language Academies in Peru, Ecuador, and Guatemala,", undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Norman, William M., "Positional and Transitive Verb Roots in Quiche,", 1973 November (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Norman, William M., "Grammatical Parallelism in Quiche Ritual Language,", 1980 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Norman, William M., "Advancement Rules and Syntactic Change: The Loss of Instrumental Voice in Mayan,", 1978 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Norman, William and Lyle Campbell, "Is a Proto-Mayan Syntax Possible?,", 1976 November (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Ordóñez, Juan, "Traduccion Gramatica (tesis),", undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Otzoy, Colop and Luis Enrique Sam Colop, "Mayan Ethnicity and Modernization,", 1988 November 16-20 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Painter, Michael, "Aymara and Spanish in Southern Peru: Languages in Contact as Markers of Economic Class and Ethnic Identity,", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Paul, Benjamin D., "Entrepeneurs and Economic Inequality in San Pedro La Laguna, Guatemala: A Hundred Years of History", draft copy, 1988 March 17-19 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Paul, Benjamin D., "Identity Change in Guatemalan Community of San Pedro La Laguna: A Speculation,", undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Peñalosa, F., "Los prestamos en la narracion atateca", trabajo preparado para el IX Taller Maya, 1978 June (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Peñalosa, F., "Language Policies in Central America: Guatemala and Nicaragua", Panel 338 for the Latin American Studies Association XIV International Congress, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Pérez, B'aayil Eduardo, "Productividad Lingüística,", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Pinkerton, Sandra, "K'ekchi Ergativity", talk, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Pinkerton, Sandra, "Ejectives and Implosives in the Quichean Languages,", undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Pinkerton, Sandra, "Observations on the Tu/Vos Option in Guatemalan Ladino Spanish,", 1986 September (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Pop Caal, Antonio, "Réplica del indio a una disertación ladina,", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Pullum, Geoffrey, "The Great Eskimo Vocabular Hoax,", 1989 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Pye, Clifton, "Mayan Telegraphese: Intonational Determinants of Inflectional Development in Quiche Mayan,", 1982 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Pye, Clifton, "Language Loss in Chilcotin,", 1985 December (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Pye, Clifton and Pedro Quixtan Poz, "Precocious Passives (and Antipassives) in Quiche Mayan,", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Pye, Clifton, "The Language Abilities of Quiche Mayan Preschoolers,", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Pye, Clifton, "Towards an Anthropology of Language Acquisition" and CV, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Randall, Robert, "Ten Languages or Two?: Southern Philippine Multilingualism and Inadequacies in the Philippines' Policy on Bilingual Education,", 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reimer, R. "On Vowel Length in Mam of Todos Santos" Draft submitted to International Journal of American Linguistics, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Remington, Judith A., "Current Astronomical Practices among the Maya,", 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reynoso, Diego de, "Arte y Vocabulario en Lengua Mame Dirigido,", undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Richards, Julia B. and Richards, Michael, "Mayan Language Literacy in Guatemala: A Socio-historical Overview,", 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Richards, Julia and Richards, M. "Mayan Language Planning for Bilingual Education in Guatemala,", undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Robertson, J. "Invariant Behavior in the Formation of the Grammatical Category POLIET/FAMILIAR: A Mayan/Indo-European Comparison, "submitted to International Journal of American Linguistics, plus England's peer review and letter to the editor, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rosaldo, Renato, "Metaphors of Hierarchy in a Mayan Ritual,", 1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Salazar Tetzaguic, Manuel de Jesús, "Características de la Literatura Indígena Cakchiquel", Bachelors thesis, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sam Colop, Luis Enrique, "Basic Word Order in Quiche,", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sam Colop, Luis Enrique, "Perfil de la Creación de un Proyecto para Generar una Red de Académicos y Centros de Investigación para Guatemala", LASA, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Sherzer, Joel, "The Kuna and Columbus: Encounters and Confrontations of Discourse,", 1994 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sherzer, Joel, "Sketch of the Kuna Language,", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - SIL (Summer Institute of Linguistics) Mayan Classification, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Silverstein, Michael, "Hierarchy of Features and Ergativity,", 1976 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Silverstein, Michael, "The Uses and Utility of Ideology: Some Reflections,", 1992 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Slocum, Marianna "Tzeltal (Mayan) Noun and Verb Morphology,", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Smith, Carol, "The Origins of the National Question in Guatemala: An Hypothesis,", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Smith, Carol, "Indian Class Positions and Class Consciousness: Totonicapan in the 1970s,", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Smith, Carol and Jeff Boyer, "Central America Since 1979: Part 1,", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Smith-Stark, Thomas, "Notes on Proto-Mayan Verb Morphology", Handout for Mayanist Symposium, American Anthropological Association meeting, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Smith-Stark, Thomas, "The Plurality Split,", 1974 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Smith-Stark, Thomas, "Jilotepequeno Pocomam Phonology and Morphology, Volume I,", 1982 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Smith-Stark, Thomas, "Jilotepequeno Pocomam Phonology and Morphology, Volume II"., 1982 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Solís Fonseca, Gustavo, "Breve Manual de Sintaxis,", 1995 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Solís Fonseca, Gustavo, "Introducción en la Morfología,", 1994 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Spratt, David and Nancy Spratt, "Collected Field Reports on the Phonology of Kusal,", 1968 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Spratt, David and Nancy Spratt, "Kusal Syntax,", 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Stewart, Stephen O., "Tense/Aspect in Kekchi", American Anthropological Association meeting, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Stewart, Stephen O., "Language and Education in Guatemala", also includes a note to Nora, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Stocks, Anthony, "Ethnicity and Praxis: The Cocamilla Case", The American Anthropological Association, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Straight, Stephen H., "The Transformational-Generative Grammar of American English Kinship Terminology: A Revision of Bock's 1968 Analysis,", undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Straight, Stephen H., "Decompositional Structure in Yucatec Verbs,", undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Sturm, C., "The Resurrection of Mayan Hieroglyphics: An Examination of Their Use by Highland Maya in Modern Guatemala", includes correspondence with Nora, 1992 December 12-1993 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Sywulka, Edward F., "The Morphology of the Mam Language of Guatemala, Central America,", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Tannen, Deborah, "Spoken/Written Language and the Oral/Literate Continuum,", 1980 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Tedlock, Barbara, "Sound Texture and Metaphor in Queché Maya Ritual Language,", 1982 June (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Tedlock, Barbara, "Mayans and Mayan Studies from 2000 B.C. to A.D. 1992,", 1993 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Tedlock, Barbara, "Text and Textile: Language and Technology in the Arts of the Quiché Maya,", 1985 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Trechsel, Frank R., "Passive and Ansolutive (Antipassive) Voices in Quiche,", undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Trechsel, Frank R., Absolutives and Control in Kekchi,", circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Trechsel, Frank R., "Implications of Niuean Raising,", undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Van den Berghe, Pierre L., "Ethnic Membership and Cultural Change in Guatemala,", 1968 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Van Valin, Robert D., Jr., "Grammatical Relations in Ergative Languages,", 1980 April (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Van Valin, Robert D., Jr., "Case Marking and the Structure of the Lahkota Clause,", undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Van Valin, Robert D., Jr. and William Foley, "Chapter 6: Nexus", preliminary draft of chapter from book on functional syntax and universal grammar; includes correspondence with Nora, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Van Valin, Robert D., Jr., "Assorted,", 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Vázquez Alvarez, Juan J., "Morfología del verbo de la lengua Chol de Tila, Chiapas,", undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Warren, K.B., various articles, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Warren, K.B. project proposal for "Moral Visions and Political Violence: A Latin American Case Study", includes a letter to Nora, 1987 September 30 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Wasserstrom, Robert, various articles, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Watanabe, John M., "Illness and Essence: The Conceptualization of Sickness in a Guatemalan Indian Town,", undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Watanabe, John M., "Maya Religion,", undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Watanabe, John M., "Realities of the Soul: Ethnic Identity and Cultural Convention in Western Guatemala,", undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Watanabe, John M., "In the World of the Sun: A Cognitive Model of Mayan Cosmology,", circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Watanabe, John M., "Neither as They Imagined Nor as Others Intended: Mayas and Anthropologists in the Highlands of Guatemala Since 1969", includes correspondence, 1995 November (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Watanabe, John M., various articles and correspondence, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Watanabe, John M., "From Saints to Shibboleths: Image, Structure, and Identity in Mayan Religious Syncretism,", 1988 September (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Watanabe, John M., "Elusive Essences: Souls and Social Identity in Two Highland Maya Communities", includes correspondence with Nora, 1988 July (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Watanabe, John M., "In the World of the Sun: A Cognitive Model of Mayan Cosmology,", undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Watanabe, John M., Notes on Chimbaal Mam by John Watanabe and personal correspondence, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - White, J.S., "Hot and Cold and Just Right in Tojolabal,", undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - White, J.S., "It's Impolite to State (And Worse to Point): Linguistics and the Tojolabal Occult", reading draft; includes a handout, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - White, Leslie A., "Culturological vs. Psychological Interpretations of Human Behavior,", 1947 December (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Wilhite, M., "The Lexicon of Weaving: Acquisition and Development", American Anthropological Association meeting, 1976 November 18 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Witkowski, Stanley R. and Cecil H. Brown, "Lexical Universals,", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Witkowski, Stanley R. and Cecil H. Brown, "Various articles,", 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Witkowski, Stanley R. and William F. Harrison, "Various articles,", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Witkowski, Stanley R., Cecil H. Brown, and Paul K. Chase, "Where do Tree Terms Come From?,", undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Woolard, Kathryn A., "Various articles,", 1989-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Woolard, Kathryn A. and Susan Gal, "Constructing Languages and Publics: Authority and Representation, ". and Susan Gal, "Constructing Languages and Publics: Authority and Representation,", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Yool Gomez, J., "Informacion sobre el poema y su autor,", 1988 June 21 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - York, Kenneth and Nora C. England, "Cultural Factors in University Programs for Mississippi Choctaws: A Dialogue", American Anthropological Association, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Zepeda, Ofelia, "O'odham Poetics and a Sense of Self,", 1996 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Social Stratification and Attitudes Toward Bilingual Education: An Ecuadorian Case, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series II: Bound Publications by Others
  - Subseries I: Theses
    - Benito Pérez, José G., Orden Básico y Pragmática de las Voces en Poqom, 2016 November (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Can Pixabaj, Telma, La Topicalización en K'ichee': Una Perspectiva Discursiva, 2004 July (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Carrillo Padilla, Norma N., La Derivación Gramatical del Dialecto Cakchiquel de Santa Maria de Jesus, 1980 November (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Cuz Mucu, Andres, Ambitos de uso del Idioma Q'eqchi' por los estudiantes indígenas de Cobán, 1989 September (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Esquit Choy, "Alberto, Analisis del Discurso Matrimonial Kaqchikel,", 1994 March (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Flinspach, Susan L., Language Manipulation in the Basque Nationalist Movement: The Emergence of Batua, 1982 May (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Gutiérrez Díaz, Juan C. Estructura de la cláusula simple, predicación primaria y predicación secundaria en el mixe de Tlahuitoltepec, 2014 November (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Lopez Ixcoy, Candelaria, Los Demostrativos en K'ichee', 1999 April (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Mateo Pedro, Pedro, Proceso de Cambio y Difusión en el Chuj de San Sebastián Coatán y en el Q'anjob'al de San Miguel Acatán y de Santa Eulalia en la Generación Joven, 2000 November (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Peralta Ramirez, Valentin, Tipos de Construcciones Causativas en el Nahuatl de Amanalco, Tetzcoco Edo. de Mexico, 2003 January (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Pérez González, Jaime, Predicados expresivos e ideófonos en tseltal, 2012 August (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Pérez Vail, José R., La inversión y la obviación en el mam de Cajolá, 2014 February (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Sis Iboy, María J., K'ichee'jay Riachi ¿La E Ka'iib Chi Ch'ab'al?, 2002 December (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Sam Colophon, Luis E., Hacia una propuesta de ley de Educación Bilingüe, 1983 August (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Zemp, Guido, Las influencias léxicas del español en el idioma mam, 1999 April (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Subseries II: Collected Publications
    - Bound Typescript by Gates of Basseta's Quiche Vocabulary, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Bulletin of the Public Museum of the City of Milkwaukee, Ethnobotany of the Meskwaki Indians, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Rabbinal - Achí, Ballet - Drama de los Indios Quiches de Guatemala, Georges Raynaud, Guatemala, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - !Extra! Contenido (revista) De la cueva a la piramide, Volumen 1 México ante de los Aztcas, Mayo 1978, paperback, 128 pp., 1978 May (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - ja' slo'il jun vinik chamula, k'uxi ch'i tal; monolingual comic in Tzotzil; paperback, staple binding; 15 pp. Mexico 1978, 1978 June (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Pop Wuj (Libro de Acontecimientos), 1979 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Neuenswander, Helen, Instituto Linguistico de Verano de Centro America: El Dualismo: una fenómeno lingüístico y cultural entre el pueblo Cubulco Achi (Maya), 1986 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Townsend, Paul, Instituto Linguistico de Verano de Centro America: Noun Prases in Cotzal Ixil, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - McArthur, Harry, Instituto Linguistico de Verano de Centro America: The Role of Ancestors in the Daily Life of the Aguacatec (Maya), 1986 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Ley de la Academia de las Lenguas Mayas de Guatemala, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Naj Unin Yetoj No' Swakax, Naj Txonwom Yetoj Yistil, Maltin K'uxum Us Yuu Naj Pel Mekel Ana (El Niño y su Torito, El Comerciante y Su Esposa, Martin Comemoscas de Don Pedro Miguel Say) Ediciones IXIM; trilingual in Q;anjob'al Spanish, and English; paperba, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Die Welt der Maya: Mexiko, Guatemala, Belize. Geo special, Nr. 5, 1993 October (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Mitos de actualidad. Crónica Semanal, año VII, No. 340, Guatemala, 26 de agosto al 1 de septiembre de 1994, 1994 September 1 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Rukorb’aal Tz’ihb’anik Poqomam Q’orb’al, manual de redacción Poqomam, Guatemala, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Ri Ukemiik ri Tz’ib’anik pa K’ichee’ Ch’ab’al, manual de redacción K'ichee', Saqijik, Guatemala, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Yunal Stxolilal Kotz'ib'on Koti', manual de redacción Q'anjob'al, Guatemala, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Tales and Legend of the Q'anjob'al Maya, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Prosecution by Proxy: The Civil Patrols in Guatemala by Alice Jay, published by the Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Center for Human Rights. Paperback, 72pp plus unnumbered pages of photos and appendices. There is a folder press release inserted in the front c, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Patrimonio Arqueológico Indígena en Chile: Reflexiones y Propuestas de Gestión (UNESCO), Santiago, Chile, 1998 November (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - The Myrna Mack Case: An Update, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - El Pensamiento De Las Montañas: Coconucos, Guambianos, Paeces, Yanaconas by Hugo Pórtela Guarin, Columbia, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Kaqetamaj usik'ixik, utz'ib'axik ri K'iche' Ch'ab'al, Guatemala, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Informe de verificación de la Misión de las Naciones Unidas en Guatemala: Los pueblos indígenas de guatemala la superación de la discriminación en el marco de los acuerdos de paz, 2001 September (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Derechos, Reforma y La Justicia y Pueblo Mapuche, Chile, 2002 May 10 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Pi-najuuyaa iquituhuaaca cuhuasiini, Vamos a escribir el idioma iquito, Primera versión, 2003 August (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Ley General de Derechos Lingüísticos de los Pueblos Indígenas en Maya y Español, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Noj a'almaj t'aanil u paajtalil u t'a'anal maasewal t'aano'ob ich maaya yeetel kaastlan t'an - Ley general de derechos lingüísticos de los pueblos indígenas en maya y español. Mérida, Yucatán, México, 2004 February (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Mecanismo de Apoyo a los Pueblos Indígenas: Oxlajuj Tz'kin, 2005-2008 (Box 6, Folder 14)